We have a lot of choices
to make about our diet.
Add to that, doing
the right thing
when it comes
to preventing
and treating a
chronic disease,
fighting a virus,
or losing weight,
and suddenly our
nutrition choices
can seem almost
overwhelming.
Well, I’m here to help.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today, it all comes down
to the shape and
support of our body,
the protection of our
organs and those things
without which we would quickly
become a gelatinous mass
— our bones!
In our first story,
we look at how those
eating plant-based diets
may be so slim, that they suffer
from a loss of bone mass.
Osteoporosis is estimated to affect
200 million people worldwide.
Literally meaning "porous bone ,"
osteoporosis is a disease
characterized by reduced bone
formation, excessive bone loss,
or a combination of both,
leading to bone fragility
and increased risk of fractures.
And bone mineral density is the
most robust and consistent predictor
of osteoporotic fracture. What can
we eat to boost our bone density?
Well, we know that increased
consumption of plant foods
is associated with increased
bone mineral density.
There's an extensive range of
micronutrients and phytochemicals
packaged within plants that can be
powerful promoters of bone health,
so healthcare professionals
should be encouraged
to advise the increased
consumption of plant-based foods,
particularly in mid-life,
irrespective of the clients
underlying dietary pattern,
meaning no matter how
much meat or junk they eat,
adding more healthy plant
foods may help prevent
the development of osteoporosis.
On the other hand, a more
animal-source nutrient pattern
has been associated with
a higher risk of fractures,
suggesting that a more animal-based
diet is related to bone fragility.
So one would expect less osteoporosis
in those eating plant-based diets,
but you don't know
until you put it to the test.
"The Incidence of osteoporosis
in vegetarians and omnivores ,"
the first study published
nearly 50 years ago,
and the density of the bones
that were measured was
significantly greater in the
vegetarians than the omnivores.
In fact, the average bone densities
of the vegetarians in their '70s
was greater than the densities
of the meat eaters in their '50s.
Bottom line, these results suggest
there's less likelihood of vegetarians
developing osteoporosis in old age.
Turns out, though, that
the researchers screwed up.
DEXA scanning, which
is what we use now,
didn't come online until the 1980s.
So the researchers were
just using regular x-rays
and they confused the readings,
such that darker bones on the x-ray
got a higher score, but that
actually means less bone,
so their conclusion should
have been the opposite
of what they claimed.
So vegetarians had
worse bone mineral density.
Fast-forward about 40 years,
by which time nine studies
had been done on thousands
of individuals, and all in all,
the results suggest that vegetarian
diets, particularly vegan diets,
are associated with lower
bone mineral density, but
the magnitude of the association
is clinically insignificant, meaning
the difference was so small as to not
really matter out in the real world,
reinforcing the fact
that vegetarian diets
have no clinically detrimental
effect on bone health.
And it is important to note
that the findings of lower
bone mineral density didn't fully
control for key confounding factors,
such as for differences
in body weight.
We know that people who are
obese have stronger bones. Why?
Because they're weight lifting 50 pounds
all day, every day, and maybe 100 pounds.
If you walked around with a
100-pound backpack every day,
your bones would grow stronger, too.
That's how you build strong
bones: weight-bearing exercise.
So people who weigh
more have denser bones.
And vegetarians, and especially
vegans, have such low rates of obesity
that no wonder, on average they
would have lower bone density.
The researchers didn't
take weight into account,
but if the difference they found isn't
even clinically significant, who cares?
As of 2009, the answer to the question,
"Is vegetarianism a serious risk
factor for osteoporotic fracture?"
the answer was no. Vegetarianism
is not a serious risk factor.
By 2018, the latest meta-analysis
on veganism, vegetarianism,
and bone mineral density,
was up to 20 studies,
involving tens of thousands
of participants, and, again,
lower bone mineral density
was found in studies
of vegetarians and vegans
compared to meat eaters.
The researchers conclude that
vegetarian and vegan diets
need to be appropriately
planned to preserve their bones.
But wait, did they account
for the obesity thing?
No, they did not.
They just used what are
called crude risk ratios,
meaning no adjustments for
confounding factors like weight,
so they didn't control for things
like age, smoking, obesity,
exercise, and so their results
are really uninterpretable.
But no one had gone through
the trouble of going back through
all those studies and making
the proper adjustments until now.
The title gives it away: "Differences
in Bone Mineral Density between
Vegetarians and Nonvegetarians
Become Marginal when
Accounting for Differences
in Body Size Factors."
Yes, bone mineral density values
were significantly lower
among vegetarians
than among nonvegetarians,
just like is the case
with nearly every study
on bone mineral density
and excess body weight.
But forget clinical significance;
these differences
even lost statistical significance
upon adjustment for body size
factors, suggesting that lower
bone mass among vegetarians
is in larger parts explained by their
lower BMI and waist circumference.
Thus, it's not so much the composition
of the diets of vegetarians and vegans
as much as it is the fact that
they become so much slimmer.
Now a small but statistically
significant difference remained
for total lower spine density,
a difference of 0.03.
This was dismissed as having little
clinical relevance, but is that true?
If you look at the reproducibility
of bone mineral density
measurements in daily medical
practice, you can see how
if you do repeat tests back-to-back,
there's some scatter
in the measurements, and
so a significant difference
really has to be more
than the inherent variation.
And indeed, expressed as
the smallest detected difference,
you really need a bone
mineral density disparity
of at least 0.05 at the spine
before it can be considered
a significant change,
and so indeed, there does appear
to be little clinical relevance.
However, even if vegetarians
and vegans basically
have the same bone density
at the same weight,
everyone who is skinny
is at risk.
Low BMI is a risk factor for
fractures, so all persons in
a low body weight category
consuming any kind of diet
should be monitored
for osteoporosis.
In our next story, we look
at the decades-old dogma
that the lack of animal protein
leads to bone loss.
For most of the last century,
a prevailing theory
within the field of
nutrition was that
by eating acid-forming
foods such as meat
we were, in essence, at
risk of peeing our bones
down the toilet.
And no wonder!
Experiments dating
back to 1920
showed over and over that if
you add meat to the diet
you get a big spike in
the amount of calcium
being lost in the urine.
And so this made total sense.
We had known since 1912
that meat was acid-
forming within the body,
and how do you buffer acid?
What are in antacid pills,
anti-acid pills like Tums?
Calcium.
Meat and eggs have a lot of
sulfur-containing amino acids,
2-5 times more than
grains and beans
that are metabolized
into sulfuric acid,
which the body buffers
with calcium.
That's why the antacids like
Tums are made out of calcium,
calcium can buffer acid.
And where is calcium
stored in the body?
The skeleton.
So the thinking was that
every time we ate a steak
our body would pull
calcium from our bones,
bit by bit, and over time
this could lead to osteoporosis.
Based on 26 such studies
every 40 grams of protein
we add to your daily diet we pee
out an extra 50mg of calcium.
And look we only have about 2 pounds
of calcium in our skeleton,
so the loss of 50
a day would mean
losing close to 2% of
bone calcium every year.
And so by the end
of the 20th century,
there was little doubt
that acid-forming diets
would dissolve our bones away.
But if you actually
look at all the studies
done on protein intake
and bone health,
that's not what you find.
So, where's the
flaw in our logic?
Meat leads to acid,
which leads to calcium loss,
which leads to bone loss, right?
Well, it's uncontroversial that protein
results in greater calcium excretion,
but we've just been assuming
it's coming from the bone—
I mean where else
could the extra calcium
dumped in our urine be coming
from but from our bones?
This is the study that appeared
to solve the mystery.
An intrepid group of researchers tried
feeding a bunch of volunteers
radioactive calcium and then putting
them on a high protein diet.
What happens when you put people
on a high protein diet?
The amount of calcium in
their urine shoots up,
and indeed that's
just what happened.
But here's the big question:
Was that extra calcium in their
urine radioactive or not?
And to everyone's surprise
it was radioactive.
Meaning, that the excess
calcium in their urine
was coming from their diet!
Remember they were feeding
them radioactive calcium.
So the excess calcium in their urine
wasn't coming from their bones,
but from what
they were eating.
What seemed to be
happening is that
excess protein consumption
boosted calcium absorption,
from down around
19% up to 26%.
So all of a sudden there was all
this extra calcium in the blood
so presumably the kidneys are like,
"Whoa what are we going
to do with it all?"
So they dump it
in the urine.
90% of the extra calcium in the
urine after eating a steak
doesn't appear to be coming from
our bones but from our diet.
We're not sure why protein
boosts calcium absorption.
Maybe the protein increases
the solubility of calcium
by stimulating stomach
acid production?
Whatever the reason,
yes, more calcium lost,
but more calcium gained
such that in the end
most of that extra
calcium is accounted for.
So in effect more calcium is
lost in the urine stream,
but may be compensated
by less loss of calcium
through the fecal stream.
This was repeated with
even more extreme diets—
an acid-forming five burgers a day
worth of animal protein diet
that limited fruits
and vegetables
versus an alkaline diet emphasizing
fruits and vegetables.
More calcium in the
urine on burgers,
but significantly greater
calcium absorption
such that at the end it
was pretty much a wash.
Other studies have also since
supported this interpretation.
Here's an ingenious one:
Feed people a high
animal protein diet,
but with an alkali salt
to neutralize the acid.
The old thinking would
predict that there
would be no calcium loss since there
is no excess acid to buffer.
But no! Even though the
acid load was neutralized
there was still the
excess urinary calcium,
consistent with the
radioactive isotope study,
challenging this long-standing dogma
that animal protein consumption
results in an acidosis that promotes
the excess excretion of calcium.
Finally today, we look at
how the galactose in milk
may explain why
milk consumption
has been associated with
significantly higher risk
of hip fractures, cancer,
and premature death.
Milk is touted to
build strong bones,
but a compilation of all the
best studies found no association
between milk consumption
and hip fracture risk,
so drinking milk as an
adult might not help bones
but what about
in adolescence?
Harvard researchers decided
to put it to the test.
Studies have shown that
greater milk consumption
during childhood and adolescence
contributes to peak bone mass
and is therefore
expected to help
avoid osteoporosis and
bone fractures in later life.
But that's not
what they found.
Milk consumption during teenage
years was not associated
with a lower risk of hip fracture.
If anything milk consumption
was associated with
a borderline increase in fracture risk in men.
It appears that the
extra boost in total body
bone mineral density you get
from getting extra calcium
is lost within a few years even if
you keep the calcium supplementation up.
This suggests a partial explanation
for the long-standing enigma
that hip fracture rates
are highest in populations
with the greatest
milk consumption.
Maybe an explanation
why they’re not lower,
but why would
they be higher?
This enigma irked a
Swedish research team,
puzzled because studies
again and again had shown
a tendency of a higher risk of fracture
with a higher intake of milk.
Well there is a rare birth
defect called galactosemia,
where babies are born
without the enzymes needed
to detoxify the galactose
found in milk so they end up
with elevated levels of
galactose in their blood,
which can causes bone
loss even as kids.
So maybe, the Swedish
researchers figured,
even in normal people that
can detoxify the stuff,
it might not be good for the bones
to be drinking it every day.
And galactose doesn’t
just hurt the bones.
That’s what scientists use to cause
premature aging in lab animals.
They slip them a
little galactose
and you can shorten
their lifespan,
cause oxidative stress,
inflammation, brain degeneration,
just with the equivalent of like 1-2 glasses
of milks worth of galactose a day.
We’re not rats,
though—
but given the high amount
of galactose in milk,
recommendations to increase milk
intake for prevention of fractures
could be a conceivable
contradiction,
so they decided
to put it to the test,
looking at milk
intake and mortality
as well as fracture risk
to test their theory.
A hundred thousand
men and women
followed for up
to 20 years-
what did they find?
Milk drinking women
had higher rates
of death, more heart disease, significantly
more cancer for each glass of milk.
Three glasses a day was associated
with nearly twice the risk of death.
And they had significantly more
bone and hip fractures too.
Men in a separate study
also had a higher rate
of death with higher
milk consumption
but at least they didn’t have
higher fracture rates.
So a dose dependent higher rate
of both mortality and fracture
in women and a higher rate of
mortality in men with milk intake,
but the opposite for other dairy
products like soured milk and yogurt,
which would go along with
the galactose theory,
since bacteria can ferment
away some of the lactose.
To prove it though, we need
a randomized controlled trial
to examine the effect of milk intake
on mortality and fractures.
As the accompanying
editorial pointed out,
we better find this out
soon as milk consumption
is on the rise
around the world.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
Or go to your local public
library for that matter.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.